Guide to the Marion T. Plyler Papers, circa 1832-1950
Duke University. University Archives
Marion T. Plyler papers circa 1832-1950
Duke University. University Archives
Plyler, Marion T.
1 linear feet Extent: 750 Items
Marion Timothy Plyler was born in Iredell County, N.C., near Statesville in 1867. He graduated from Trinity College in 1892 with a B. A. degree and played on the school's first football team. He earned his M. A. degree at Trinity in 1897 and received his Doctor of Divinity degree from Duke University in 1937. Additionally, Dr. Plyler received the M. A. degree and the D. D. degree from the University of North Carolina in 1905 and 1931, respectively. Dr. Plyler was ordained as a minister in the Methodist Church in 1892. Contains typescripts, correspondence, and printed matter, with the bulk of the material consisting of the manuscript of Dr. Plyler's unpublished biography of William Preston Few, written in 1948-1949, as well as copies of Few's writings and addresses. The collection ranges in date from 1832-1950.
uaplyler
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Marion T. Plyler Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1971.
Biographical Note
Marion Timothy Plyler was born in Iredell County, N.C., near Statesville in 1867. He was the son of Robert Conrad Plyler and Mary Kimball Plyler. He received his boyhood education in the Iredell County schools and a boarding school in Mooresville. He graduated from Trinity College in 1892 with a B. A. degree and played on the school's first football team. He earned his M. A. degree at Trinity in 1897 and received his Doctor of Divinity degree from Duke University in 1937. Additionally, Dr. Plyler received the M. A. degree and the D. D. degree from the University of North Carolina in 1905 and 1931, respectively.
Dr. Plyler was ordained as a minister in the Methodist Church in 1892 and served several pastorates throughout North Carolina before moving to Durham in 1919. He and his twin brother, Alva, edited the NC Christian Advocate from 1926-1946 and he also helped organize the North Carolina Pastors' School and chaired its board of management for 30 years. He wrote several biographies, including an unpublished one of William Preston Few, President of Trinity College and Duke University. He was a member of Phi Beta Kappa.
On June 20, 1900, he married Epie Duncan Smith, and they had seven children. Dr. Plyler died in 1954 at age 86.
Collection Overview
Contains typescripts, correspondence, and printed matter, with the bulk of the material consisting of the manuscript of Dr. Plyler's unpublished biography of William Preston Few, written in 1948-1949, as well as copies of Few's writings and addresses. There are several folders of related printed matter, research notes, and articles, including typescripts annotated by Dr. Few and Dean Alice Baldwin. Correspondence concerns the North Carolina Pastors' School, Methodist Conference matters, and the Few biography. The collection also includes some genealogical notes and other typescripts by Dr. Plyler. The collection ranges in date from 1832-1950.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Baldwin, Alice M. (Alice Mary), 1879-1960; Few, William Preston, 1867-1940; Plyler, Marion Timothy, 1867-1954
Related Material
William Preston Few records and papers, 1814-1971 (bulk 1911-1940)
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Genealogy and Obituary, including letters, circa 1832 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1947
  - Correspondence, 1948-1950
  - James B. Duke - The Man, by George G. Allen, 1933 Manuscripts
  - Report on Recent Cooperative Activities between Duke University and the University of North Carolina, by the Joint Committee on Intellectual Cooperation, 1937
  - Few Biography Research
  - VIII. College for Women, [Few, William P.], circa 1939
  - President Few and the Woman's College, Baldwin, Alice M.
  - Printed matter, Few speeches
  - Reports (Few, William P.)
  - Writings (Few, William P.), 1905-1910
  - Writings (Few, William P.), 1911-1924
  - Writings (Few, William P.), 1925-1929
  - Writings (Few, William P.), 1930-1936 (Box 2)
  - Writings (Few, William P.), 1936-1940, undated
  - Few Biography, typescript, I. Years of Preparation
  - Few Biography, typescript, II. Trinity College
  - Few Biography, typescript, IV. Chiefly Personal
  - Few Biography, typescript, V. The Final Decade
  - Few Biography, typescript, VI. Funeral Services
  - Few Biography, typescript, VII. Memorial Services, 1941
  - Few Biography, typescript, VIII. Appendices